

🛘 (+47) 411 42 466 | 🗷 erik@i-solution.de | Rº Erik Kusch | 🕲 0000-0002-4984-7646 | 🌃 erikkusch.com | 🖫 ErikKusch | 💆 KuschErik

Research Profile

I am a biostatistican and data scientist specialised in streamlining work-flows as well as integrating and analysing heterogeneous data products. I use and develop quantitative tools to study the impacts of climate change and investigate the resilience of system at macro-scales to understand trajectories through time and space. My current work includes software development for climate data retrieval and aggregation as well as inference, analysis, and simulation of ecological networks.

Education

PhD in Biology; Specialisation on Ecoinformatics, Data Analysis and Biodiversity

01/2020 - 04/2023

AARHUS UNIVERSITY (AU) & OXFORD UNIVERSITY (OX)

Dissertation: A Macroecological Perspective to Ecological Networks - Exploring the Impacts of Climate-Driven Biodiversity

Change & Contrasting and Benchmarking Network Inference Approaches

M.Sc. in Biology; Specialisation on Biodiversity, Ecology and Evolution

08/2017 - 08/2019

Évora, Portugal

Helsinki, Finland

University of Bergen (UiB) & Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center (Nansen)

Thesis: Inferring Vegetation Memory From Remote Sensing Data And Identifying Causal Links To Plant Function

B.Sc. in Biology 10/2013 - 07/2017

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD) & UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN (UIB)

Thesis: Remote Sensing And Predicting Shifts In Biome Distribution And Resilience Using NDVI Data

Specialised Training

Invasive Species Monitoring with Remote Sensing

NASA'S APPLIED REMOTE SENSING TRAINING (ARSET) 11/08/2024 - 28/08/2024

Open, Reproducible, and Transparent Science in Ecology Finse, Norway

University of Bergen 14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022

7th Edition Species Distribution Modelling Course

University of Évora, Science Retreats 26/04/2021 - 02/05/2021

An Introduction to Bayesian Statistics Glasgow, Scotland

University of Glasgow 06/04/2021 - 16/04/2021

Hierarchical Modelling of Species Communities with the R-package Hmsc

University of Helsinki 02/11/2020 - 06/11/2020

Modelling Challenges for Mountain Ecosystems

Hamburg, Germany

University of Hamburg 23/02/2020 - 28/02/2020

Experience _

Advisor Oslo, Norway

CICERO CENTER FOR INTERNATIONAL CLIMATE RESEARCH 09/2024 - PRESENT

Senior Engineer / Research Infrastructure Manager Oslo, Norway

Natural History Museum, University of Oslo 03/2023 - 12/2024

Visiting Researcher Onna, Japan

OKINAWA INSTITUTE FOR SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY 02/2024 - 12/2024

Research FellowBergen, Norway

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN 09/2019 - 12/2019

National Park Ranger & Environmental Education Guide Saxony, Germany

National Park Saxon-Bohemian Swiss 04/2016 - 06/2016

Research and Teaching Assistant

BEHAVIOURAL ECOLOGY RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF LEIPZIG
PRIMATE RESEARCH CENTRE, UNIVERSITY OF KYOTO
GERMAN CENTRE FOR MARINE BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH, SENCKENBERG GROUP

08/2017 - 08/2019; 03/2017 - 04/2017 07/2018 05/2017 - 07/2017

Teaching & Supervision Activity

NFDI4Biodiversity & iDiv Seasonal School on Data Management in Biodiversity and Environmental Science

Course Material

AUTHOR & LECTURER

Bayesian Networks Study Group

Personal Course Web Page

AUTHOR & LECTURER

AU Bayes Study Group

Personal Course Web Page

AUTHOR & LECTURER

Excursions into Biostatistics

♦ Course Web Page

AUTHOR & LECTURER

An Introduction to Biostatistics Using R

♦ Course Web Page

AUTHOR & LECTURER

Biological Research in Theory and Praxis (BFTP)

♦ Course Web Page Aarhus University

Author **Teaching Assistant**

Aarhus University

Applied Statistics
Statistical and Geospatial Modelling

22/03/2021 - 14/05/2021 03/09/2020 - 18/12/2020

GEOSPATIAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS

27/10/2020 - 18/12/2020

Instructor & Advisor

ECOINFORMATICS & BIODIVERSITY MASTERS SEMINARS (EBMS), AARHUS UNIVERSITY

CENTRE OF EXCELLENCE IN BIODIVERSITY EDUCATION (BIOCEED), UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

03/02/2021 - 05/05/2021

08/2017 - 07/2018

Talks & Workshops _

Integrating Ecological Networks in Macroecological Research

Oslo, Norway

AUTHOR & SPEAKER, STADIS TANGLED BANK-SEMINARS

17/08/2023

Accessing and Referencing GBIF Data for Research
AUTHOR & SPEAKER, LIVING NORWAY COLLOQUIUM 2023

Trondheim, Norway 24/05/2023

State-of-the-Art Climate Data for Macroecologists with the KrigR Pipeline

Aarhus, Denmark

AUTHOR & SPEAKER, 5TH CONFERENCE OF NORDIC SOCIETY OIKOS 2022

07/07/2022

AUTHOR & SPEAKER, BIOCHANGE METHODS WORKSHOPS

12/11/2020

Ecological Network Inference - Pipedream or Pipeline

Oxford, England

Invited Speaker, SalGo Team, University of Oxford

22/05/2022

KrigR - Climate Data For Your Spatial Study

Spatial Patterns of Plant Performance

SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020

25/06/2020

Identifying Ecological-Memory Patterns in Drylands using Remote Sensing

SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY FOR ECOLOGICAL MODELLING CONFERENCE 2019

Bergen, Norway 15/03/2019

04/10/2019

Invited Speaker, BIO Day, University of Bergen

Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data

Glasgow, Scotland

Invited speaker, Spatial Ecology Group, University of Glasgow

09/01/2019

Writing

A Yarnball of Frayed Strings - Communication, Impact & Cohesion of European Biodiversity Research Infrastructures

ERIK KUSCH, ALLAN T. SOUZA, YI-MING GAN, CARRIE ANDREW

Rx Preprint - 2024

TwinEco: A Unified Framework for Dynamic Data-Driven Digital Twins in Ecology

Taimur Khan, Koen de Koning, Dag Endresen, Desalegn Chala, **Erik Kusch**

Rx Preprint - 2024

Prototype biodiversity digital twin: crop wild relatives genetic resources for food security

DESALEGN CHALA, **ERIK KUSCH**, CLAUS WEILAND, CARRIE ANDREW, JONAS GRIEB, TUOMAS ROSSI, TOMAS MARTINOVIC, DAG ENDRESEN

Research Ideas and Outcomes - 2024

Plant trait and vegetation data along a 1314 m elevation gradient with fire history in Puna grasslands, Perú

AUD HALBRITTER, VIGDIS VANDVIK, SEHOYA COTNER, [...], ERIK KUSCH, [...], BRIAN ENQUIST

Mature Scientific Data - 2024

A Novel Simulation Framework for Validation of Ecological Network Inference

ERIK KUSCH*, ANNA C. VINTON* (* ... JOINT FIRST-AUTHORSHIP)

Rx Preprint - 2023

Ecological Network Resilience & Extinction Proxies - Updating Projections of Ecological Networks

ERIK KUSCH, ALEJANDRO ORDONEZ

Rx Preprint - 2023

Ecological Network Inference is not Consistent Across Scales or Approaches

ERIK KUSCH, MALYON BIMLER, JAMES A. LUTZ, ALEJANDRO ORDONEZ

Rx Preprint - 2023

NetworkExtinction - R Package to Simulate Extinction Propagation & Rewiring Potential in Ecological Networks

M.Isidora Ávila-Thieme*, **Erik Kusch***, Derek Corcoran*, ..., Navarrete, Pablo A. Marquet (* ... joint first-authorship)

Methods in Ecology and Evolution - 2023

MOSAIC: A Unified Trait Database to Complement Structured Population Models

Connor Bernard, Gabriel Silva Santos, [...], **Erik Kusch**, [...], Roberto Salguero-Gómez

Mature Scientific Data - 2023

A novel trophic cascade between cougars and feral donkeys shapes desert wetlands

ERICK LUNDGREN, DANIEL RAMP, OWEN MIDDLETON, EAMONN WOOSTER, ERIK KUSCH, [...], ARIAN WALLACH

🚭 Journal of Animal Ecology - 2022

Vegetation memory effects and their association with vegetation resilience in global drylands

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY, ALISTAIR SEDDON

ᡂ Journal of Ecology − 2022

KrigR - A Tool for Downloading and Statistically Downscaling Climate Reanalysis Data

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY

6 Environmental Research Letters - 2022

Reconciling high resolution climate datasets using KrigR

RICHARD DAVY, ERIK KUSCH

Environmental Research Letters - 2021

Honours & Grants & Awards _____

FOR ECOINFORMATICS DUNGEONS & DRAGONS GROUP

SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS

10/2020 Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students , Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship	Aarhus, Denmark
03/2019 Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond	Bergen, Norway
02/2019 Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret	Bergen, Norway
03/2018 Project Grant , L. Meltzers Høyskolefond	Bergen, Norway
2018/19 Scholarship , German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes)	Bonn, Germany
Awards	
10/2019 Best Poster: Student and Early Career Researcher, International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria
$10/2019 \textbf{Modeller's Choice Poster Award}, \ \text{International Society for Ecological Modelling}$	Salzburg, Austria
Extracurricular Activity	
-	
Group Leader	
Group Leader Coders & Biostatisticians of NHM, University of Oslo	08/2023 - 12/2024
-	08/2023 - 12/2024 08/2023 - 12/2024
Coders & Biostatisticians of NHM, University of Oslo	, ,
Coders & Biostatisticians of NHM, University of Oslo Natural History Museum Computational Biology Help-desk, University of Oslo	, ,
Coders & Biostatisticians of NHM, University of Oslo Natural History Museum Computational Biology Help-desk, University of Oslo Group Member	08/2023 - 12/2024
Coders & Biostatisticians of NHM, University of Oslo Natural History Museum Computational Biology Help-desk, University of Oslo Group Member STADIS – STABILITY AND DISCONTINUITY GROUP, University of Oslo	08/2023 - 12/2024 08/2023 - PRESENT
CODERS & BIOSTATISTICIANS OF NHM, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY HELP-DESK, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO Group Member STADIS – STABILITY AND DISCONTINUITY GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO STATISTICS JOURNAL CLUB, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW	08/2023 - 12/2024 08/2023 - PRESENT 03/2021 - 03/2023
CODERS & BIOSTATISTICIANS OF NHM, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY HELP-DESK, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO Group Member STADIS – STABILITY AND DISCONTINUITY GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO STATISTICS JOURNAL CLUB, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW SPATIAL SHARED-INTEREST GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW	08/2023 - 12/2024 08/2023 - PRESENT 03/2021 - 03/2023 03/2021 - 03/2023

03/2022 - 01/2023